A Guide to the Film collection FA466
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Ford Foundation, 6; Except where noted, the Ford Foundation films are only available on the original film format
  - Music Lessons, 1981; Sound, Color, 41 minutes. (Reel AV 2201, Reel AV 1924)
    An introduction to the Kodaly Method of musical instruction. Elementary students from Connecticut to California are shown learning the basic steps of singing and reading music. Filmed segments of elementary school music education in various cities throughtout the United States. Produced and edited by Joyce Chopra. Copyright 1981, the Ford Foundation.
  - My Brother's Children, 1970; Sound, Color, 52 minutes. (Reel AV 1891)
    The Family Planning Council of Nigeria presents this dramatized look at efforts to support large families in rural Africa, and suggestions for improving conditions. Villagers balancing farm life, new technologies, and transitions to towns and cities, are education about family planning methods and new health options. Supported by the International Planned Parenthood Federation. Produced by DAN Productions LTD, London.
  - Nationalism, Democracy, Communism, 1958; Sound, Black & white, 1 hour 13 minutes. (Reel AV 2020A, Reel AV 2020C, Reel AV 2020B)
    Lecture 14 of the 15 part "A Changing World in the Light of History" series. Led by Arnold J. Toynbee and presented at Washington and Lee university in Lexington, Virgina. The lecture discusses the topics of nationalism ,democracy and communism on an international scale during the cold war. There is a supplemental question and answer session with the audience after the presentation. Copyright 1958, Encyclopedia Britannica Films, Inc.
  - New Images: Art in a Changing African Society, 1964; Sound, Color, 26 minutes. (Reel AV 1961)
    Film discussing the evolution of dance, sculpture, and other traditional fine art practices of the Oshogbo people of Western Nigeria. Made by Francis Speed and Ulli Beier from the University of Ibadan, Nigeria.
  - A New Look at the Sun, 1970; Sound, Color, 21 minutes. (Reel AV 1419)
    A film about solar physics and the use of a new radio heliograph used to analyze the activity of the sun using radio frequency. The Ford Foundation funded the construction of the Culgoora Radio heliograph, which is featured in the film. Produced by CSIRO Film.
  - New Mathematics in the Primary School, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 15 minutes. (Reel AV 1418)
    An educational short film produced by Education Development Center Inc, funded by the Ford Foundation. Documents the lessons and progress of a primary school math program in Nigeria and Tanzania.
  - Non Basta Solo L'alfabeto, Sound, Black & white, 16 minutes. (Reel AV 2194)
    Documentary film about the work which is carried out by the Center of Adult Education of the Union for the Struggle Against Illiteracy in southern Italy, Saradinia and Sicily. The film highlights literacy, mathematics and vocational training, community upkeep projects, and work to improve local living conditions.
  - The North Carolina Fund, Sound, Black & white, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 1954)
    Short film from the North Carolina Fund about the poverty cycle: socioeconomic patterns that develop in childhood and continue through adulthood to keep poor populations from succeeding. Funded by the Ford Foundation and others.
  - Nyiregyhazi, Sound, Color, 22 minutes (Reel AV 1993)
    Documentary on Hungarian born American pianist Ervin Nyiregyhazi recording music for the International Piano Archive funded by a Ford Foundation grant.
  - The Office Telephone, Sound, Black & white, 28 minute. (Reel AV 1779)
    Introduction to modern dial telephones, and system of operators and telephone communication in Nigeria. Produced by the Ford Foundation and the Public Authorities of Nigeria, directed by Joseph Franklin.
  - On the Move: Careers in Transportation, Sound, Color, 13 minutes. (Reel AV 1992)
    Careers in Transportation is part of an exploration film series developed by Olympus Research Corporation and the Wyoming State Department of Education in cooperation with the U.S. Office of Education, Division of Manpower Development and Training, Department of Health, Education and Welfare. The film explores the various possible careers connected to transportation.
  - On the Spring Ice, 1975; Sound, Black & white, 45 minutes. (Reel AV 1909)
    Film produced by and about the small Eskimo community of Gambell on St. Lawrence Island in Alaska. Shot during the yearly migration of the walrus, the film has footage of village activities, hunting and storing of meat, and other traditions of these Eskimo families. Copyright 1975, the Village of Gambell and Leonard Kemerling.
  - Paper Targets, Sound, Color, 23 minutes (Reel AV 1987)
    Film by William Flynn, Charles Milson and John Osborne. Original music scored by Larry Johnson. Presented to the Foundation, 1980 July, by the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston in appreciation for the 1974 matching grant for faculty enrichment and student aid.
  - People Without a Place, Sound, Black & white, 25 minutes. (Reel AV 1784)
    A film about the plight of East German refugees after World War II, told through the story of a young immigrant boy. Written and produced by Ernest Kleinberg.
  - Periodic Motions, 1960; Sound, Black & white, 33 minutes. (Reel AV 1787)
    A short educational film with Professors David Ivey and Patterson Hume of the University of Toronto, produced by Educational Services, Inc. Funded by the National Science Foundation, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the Ford Foundation as part of a course on physics.
  - Photons, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 1417)
    An educational short film produced by Educational Resources Inc as part of their course in physics for secondary school systems. With Professor John G. King of MIT.
  - Planning Your Family, Sound, Color, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 2197, Reel AV 1921)
    A dramatization of family planning programs in rural Africa. Typical life in a small village is shown, with women and families learning about their reproductive rights and new methods of birth control. Features an Afro-pop theme song about family planning, composed and played by E. K. Mensah. Produced by Anne Balfour-Fraser for the Planned Parenthood Association of Ghana.
  - Principals Conference, Sound, Black & white, 14 minutes. (Reel AV 1856, Reel AV 2190C, Reel AV 2190A, Reel AV 2190B)
    See: AV 1423.
    Footage from a discussion about a Ford Foundation program to improve school communication and performance. Working in multiple grades, the program focuses on community involvement, in-school tutoring, and teacher reflection and review. Two principals who have implemented the program are interviewed.
  - Progressive Waves, 1953; Sound, Black & white, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1843)
    Film from the "Basic Physics Series" about transverse and longitudinal waves, to be used in the classroom. Produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films, in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1953, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Quality of Life trailer, Sound, Color, 29 minutes. (Reel AV 1988)
    A trailer reel of films depicting public welfare programs funded by the Ford Foundation in the 1970s including "The Walls Come Tumbling Down", "Vera and the Law: Toward a More Effective System of Justice", "Changing Work: American Workers in Sweden", and "Technology in Public Service."
  - Reading in an Audio-Lingual Program: Beginning Spanish, Sound, Color, 17 minutes. (Reel AV 1422)
    Produced by the Foreign Language Department, Hicksville Schools, District 17, New York; footage of an elementary Spanish class doing exercises, repetition of phrases.
  - Reflections from Plane Mirrors, Sound, Black & white, 32 minutes. (Reel AV 1788)
    Edited but unfinished footage of episode about optics and light, from educational series on physics. Probably from same series as others in this collection, produced by Educational Services Inc.
  - Refrigeration and Geysers, 1957; Sound, Color, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 1802)
    Episode from an educational series produced by Encyclopedia Britannica, "Physics: the Complete Introductory Course, filmed as taught in the public schools of Pittsburgh, PA". This lesson is from the section entitled "Heat", with Professor Harvey E. White, professor of physics, University of California. Produced by Encyclopedia Britannica Films Inc.
  - The Religions of Asia, 1958; Sound, Black & white, 90 minutes. (Reel AV 1415)
    The final lecture in a series of 15 talks entitled "A Changing World in the Light of History," given by Arnold J. Toynebee at Washington & Lee University, Lexington VA. Produced by Encyclopedia Britannica.
  - Reporter Der Windrose, Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 2006)
    German
    Documentary film hosted by Peter von Zahn with a focus on the Ford Foundation and its philanthropic efforts.
  - Return of the Reluctant Prodigy, 1978; Sound, Color, 34 minutes. (Reel AV 1995)
    Documentary on Hungarian born American pianist Ervin Nyiregyhazi recording music for the International Piano Archive funded by a Ford Foundation grant. Copyright CTV Television Network 1978 Ltd.
  - Rural U.S.A. (Through Indian Eyes), 1952-1953; Sound, Black & white, 50 minutes. (Reel AV 1344)
    Produced in 1952-1953 upon the occasion of a visit to the USA from a group of Indian dignitaries, focused on agriculture and farm technology. Includes the Department of Agriculture, the Tuskegee Institute, and various farms and communities throughout the south and southwest parts of the country. Narrated by M.S. Sundaram, produced by Charles Linko. Copyright retained by Ford Foundation.
  - Save the Children, 1974; Sound, Color, 2 hours. (Reel AV 2014)
    Conditions Governing Accessn note
    A documentary film that recorded the concert held in Chicago in 1972 as part of Jesse Jackson’s Operation PUSH exposition. Includes performances by Marvin Gaye, The Staple Singers, The Temptations, The Chi-Lites, The Main Ingredient, The O’Jays, Isaac Hayes, Zulema, The Cannonball Adderly Quintet, Albertina Walker, The Push Mass Choir, Loretta Oliver, Rev. James Cleveland, Bill Withers, Curtis Mayfield, Sammy Davis, Jr. Roberta Flack, Quincy Jones, Gladys Knight and the Pips, Jerry Butler, Brenda Lee Eager, Nancy Wilson, The Jackson 5 and Jackie Verdell. Also featured Rev. Jesse Jackson, Rev. Willie Barrow, Don Cornelius, Yvonne Daniels, Ossie Davis, Dick Gregory, Rev. Henry Hardy, Smokey Robinson, Richard Roundtree, Bill Rusell and Kim Weston. Directed by Stan Lathan and Narrated by Matt Robinson. Copyright 1974, Stellar Productions, Inc.
  - Scenes of Center for Advanced Study in Behavioral Sciences, Early 1950s; Silent, Black & White, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 2196)
    Unedited footage from the early 1950s of various scenes at the Center for Advanced Study in Behavioral Sciences in Standford, California.
  - Scholarship Award Meeting, 1955 September 7; Silent, Black & white negative, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1878)
    Meeting at the Palmer House.
  - Shape, Silent, Color, 13 minutes. (Reel AV 2002, Reel AV 1895, Reel AV 2001, Reel AV 1899)
    Seemingly stock footage of shapes found nature, architecture, human activity, and fine art: silhouettes of buildings and bridges, shadows of humans at play, natural forms like branches and flowers, and depictions of shape in paintings and sculptures. From Roehmer, Young & Associates.
  - Simple Harmonic Motion, 1953; Sound, Black & white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 1950)
    Short educational film produced in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers, from its basic physics series. Copyright 1953, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Skies of the Andes, Sound, Color, 29 minutes. (Reel AV 1982)
    Documentary on astronomy in Chile and the creation of the largest telescope on the South American continent. The telescope was funded by the Ford Foundation and the National Science Foundation for the Cerro Tololo Inter-American Observatory in Tololo, Chile.
  - Speed of Light, Sound, Black & white, 21 minutes. (Reel AV 1986)
    An educational film on the velocity of light in air and water funded by the National Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics.
  - Stationary Longitudinal Waves, 1953; Sound, Black & white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 1880)
    One episode from the Basic Physics series produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films, in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1953, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Stationary Transverse Waves, 1953; Sound, Black & white, 10 minutes. (Reel AV 1883)
  - Straight Line Kinematics, 1959; Sound, Black & white, 28 minutes. (Reel AV 1800)
    A short educational film about the study of motion, with Professor Everett M. Hefner of University of Rochester. Produced by Educational Services, Inc. Funded by the National Science Foundation, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the Ford Foundation as part of a course on physics for secondary schools.
  - The Stranger, Sound, Color, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 1841, Reel AV 2226)
    Dramatized story of government training program for young Indians to become agricultural specialists, working in rural India to improve traditional farming technologies. Written and produced by Lloyd E. Young. Presented by the Indian government with the assistance of the Ford Foundation.
  - Studies in Nigerian Dances, Sound, Black & white, 7 minutes. (Reel AV 1844)
    Unedited footage of tribesmen performing native dances in villages in Nigeria
  - Studio Watts Tape: Addendum, 1970; Sound, Color, 4 minutes. (Reel AV 1980)
    Ford Foundation grant # 69-265 GRANTEE NARRATIVE REPORT OF 1970 March. Film contains four promotional commercials for Studio Watts, Los Angeles Learning Center for the Arts.
  - Technology in Public Service, Sound, Color, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 2017, Reel AV 1958)
    A Films Incorporated presentation about the development of new technology to improve living conditions in urban areas. A research and development unit called Public Technology Inc (PTI) partners with local governments and private investors to find and solve problems of transporation, high-occupancy housing, waste removal, etc. Presented by the Ford Foundation, in association with Nell Cox Films Inc. Produced and directed by Hilary Harris.
  - Television Teaching Demonstration: Fifth Grade Reading Lesson 27, Sound, Black & white, 27 minutes. (Reel AV 1984)
    Reading lesson for fifth grade students produced by WQED Pittsburgh Station. TV Teaching Demonstration was an experiment in using TV as part of daily basic instruction in the classroom.
  - Television Teaching Demonstration: Fifth Grade Reading Lesson 36, Sound, Black & white, 31 minutes. (Reel AV 1985)
  - That Our Children Will Not Die, 1978; Silent, 60 minutes. (Reel AV 2209B, Reel AV 2210A, Reel AV 2208B, Reel AV 2209A, Reel AV 2217B, Reel AV 2208A, Reel AV 1968, Reel AV 2214A, Reel AV 2210B, Reel AV 2215, Reel AV 2214B, Reel AV 2216B, Reel AV 2222B, Reel AV 2216A, Reel AV 2222A, Reel AV 2217A)
    Soundtrack available separately, in multiple languages.
    An analysis of child health and living conditions in impoverished regions of Nigeria. Improved access to technology and well-train physicians are shown to be powerful tools, as well as localized programs and education to help villagers. With Professor O. Ransome-Kuti, director of the Institute of Child Health, University of Lagos, supported by the Ford Foundation. Produced, directed and edited by Joyce Chopra. Copyright 1978, Ford Foundation.
    Community health aides; Community health services; Public health; Nigeria; Nurse practitioners
  - That's Show Business, Sound, no picture, 26 minutes. (Reel AV 1427)
    In Spanish
    Soundtrack only to unknown film (possibly an episode of Continental Classroom.
  - They Call It Wildcat, 1974; Sound, Color, 36 minutes. (Reel AV 2220B, Reel AV 2220A, Reel AV 1799, Reel AV 2199, Reel AV 2220C)
    Documentary about an employment program for recovering addicts and ex-convicts in New York City: a joint rehabilitation venture between local, state, and federal governments, utilizing methadone treatment, job training, Medicare benefits, and tutoring. The Wildcat Service Corp operated the Supported Work Program, developed by the Vera Institute of Justice, in cooperation with the NYC Department of Employment, the US Department of Labor, and others. Directed and produced by George C. Stoney. Presented by the Ford Foundation (copyright 1974).
  - Tomorrow We'll See What Happens, 1973; Sound, Black & white, 30 minutes. (Reel AV 2198, Reel AV 1796, Reel AV 2206)
    Grantee film about three public schools in Los Angeles, CA who, facing issues of urban poverty, declining morale, and poor communication, adopted the Tutorial Community Project, a system of tutoring initiatives. Presented by Films Incorporated; copyright Ford Foundation, 1973.
  - Triumph of Technology: Flight from Land into Cities, 1956-1957; Sound, Black & white, 59 minutes. (Reel AV 2015 C, Reel AV 2015 B, Reel AV 2015 A)
    Scope and Content note
    Lecture 13 of a 15 part lecture series "A Changing World in the Light of Technology" presented by Arnold J. Toynbee at Washington and Lee University in Lexington, Virgina. Tonynbee details modernization, world migrations patterns, and rural to urban migrations. Copyright Encyclopedia Britannica Films, inc. 1958.
  - Turning Around:A Look At Neighborhoog Housing Services, 1974; Sound, Color, 22 minutes. (Reel AV 1797, Reel AV 2186, Reel AV 2218A, Reel AV 2218B, Reel AV 2218C)
    A look at neighborhood housing services, modern trends in population movement, and the practice among banks and governments of abandoning poor neighborhoods, particularly in urban settings. Presented by the Ford Foundation in cooperation with the Urban Reinvestment Task Force of the Federal Home Loan Bank Board and the US Department of Housing and Urban Development. Produced and directed by Len Appelson. Copyright maintained by Ford Foundation.
  - Under One Roof, Sound, Color, 24 minutes. (Reel AV 1777)
    A film by Frank Beaver about population management in the South: costs of child-raising, the development of birth control, and the importance of family planning. Presented by the Carolina Population Center.
  - Uniform Circular Motion, 1951; Sound, Black & white, 5 minutes. (Reel AV 1845)
    Film from the"Basic Physics Series" about uniform circular motion and velocity, to be used in the classroom. Produced by McGraw-Hill Text Films, in collaboration with the Visual Aids Committee of the American Association of Physics Teachers. Copyright 1951, McGraw-Hill Book Company.
  - Universal Gravitation, Sound, Black & white, 31 minutes. (Reel AV 1983)
    An educational film on universal gravitation funded by the National Science Foundation, Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and Ford Foundation as part of its course in physics for secondary schools.
  - Vera and the Law, 1975; Sound, Color, 40 minutes. (Reel AV 1430)
    Film about the programs and activities of developed by the Vera Institute of Justice, "a private nonprofit corporation that works with police, courts, and social agencies to help make the justice system more efficient and fair". Produced by the Ford Foundation.
  - Village of Hope, 1956; Sound, Color, 38 minutes. (Reel AV 1795)
    Film produced by the Government of India, from their Community Projects administration. The program divides issues of poverty, sanitation, and education in rural villages as part of "old" (colonial) India, and new technologies and efforts to overcome these challenges as Young India. Funded by the Ford Foundation, copyright 1956.
  - The Walls Come Tumbling Down, 1975; Sound, Color, 30 minutes. Available on DVD. (Reel AV 2205, Reel AV 2200, Reel AV 2187, Reel AV 2211, Reel AV 1345, Reel AV 2202)
    Film about the Housing Authority struggle in St. Louis in 1969 over tenement housing focused on the Pruitt-Igoe urban housing project. It examines the resident-management program in public housing projects in St. Louis. The film shows how the program has solved many of the problems of the residents and relieved the atmosphere of confrontation which plagued public housing in St. Louis before the introduction of the program. Copyright Ford Foundation, 1975.
    Series Statement
    Ford Foundation Films About Alternatives
    Public housing
  - Welcome to the Working Worlds!, Sound, Color, 20 minutes. (Reel AV 2008)
    An introduction film to a 13 part series each exploring various occupational clusters including natural resources/environment, construction, manufacturing, transportation, marketing and distribution, business and personal services, agribusiness and food production, hospitality and recreation, health, education, fine arts and the social sciences, public service, business office, and communications and media.
  - We're Ni! He is a Mad Man, Sound, Color, 27 minutes. (Reel AV 1981)
    A documentary for the Human Ecology Fund and directed by Raymond Prince, MD. Section of Transcultural Psychiatric Studies, McGill University. The film documents psychiatric disorders and Yerubic medicine in Yeruba, Nigeria. The documentary includes footage of diagnosis, treatment, care of patients, spiritual healing ceremonies, male and female cult practices, and comparisons of traditional Yerubic religion, Islam and Christianity?s relationship to psychiatric illness. Contains footage of animal sacrifice and female nudity.
  - What Happened in Seattle? The Origins of a School Desegregation Plan, Sound, Color, 43 minutes. (Reel AV 1978)
    Ford Foundation funded documentary on community led voluntary action of school desegregation from 1978 through the early 1980s.
  - World Cultures, Sound, Black & white, 25 minutes. (Reel AV 1853, Reel AV 2016B, Reel AV 2016A, Reel AV 2191B, Reel AV 2191A)
    Part of Ruth George Dobson's course in high school curriculum created for WQED Pittsurgh, Miss Dobson interviews Ford Foundation artist Ted Conut. They discuss his experience in Korea during the 1950s while working for the United Nations Film and TV Unit as well as royal court musicans, buddishism, technology, architecture, farming, poverty and family life.
- Frederick W. Knipe, 7
  Frederick Knipe was a staff member of the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation.
  Alphabetically.
  The RAC has several silent films from the 1930s about the Tirana River Project in Albania and the efforts to combat malaria throughout the Balkans and in India.
  - Albania: Durazzo, Tirana, 1930-1937; Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel IV 2 A17 Fb 4, Reel AV 806)
    Footage from malaria efforts in Albania (1930-1937), Durazzo (1930-1932), and Tirana (1933-1935). Scenes of drainage project, salinification of lagoon, killing mosquitoes with salt, Dr. Lewis Hackett, Knipe opening a dike.
  - Albania: Porto Romano, 1932; Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes. Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 807, Reel IV 2 A17 Fb 5)
    1932 footage of the lagoon in Porto Romano: automatic tide gates, canal entrance; also the lab and headquarters at Tirana.
  - Albania: Shokoset, Tirana, Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes, Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 808, Reel IV 2 A17 Fb 6)
    Footage of canal construction and usage
  - Albania: Tirana Part I, Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes, Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 809, Reel IV 2 A17 Fb 7)
    Tirana River Project: footage of Isuurush Canal and Siphon Dam on the Llana River
  - Albania: Tirana Part II, Silent, Black & white, 10 minutes, Only available on original 16mm film. (Reel AV 810, Reel IV 2 A17 Fb 8)